hey guys this looks like a fun one it
says what's the angle we want to know
this angle right here this is day 11 of
our Advent calendar for the month of
December we're going to solve 31 Katrina
ad puzzles in 31 days I just remembered
something somebody said it was hard to
see the yellow against white so let's
make this thing black so now you can see
there's two circles and the angle I
think it's safe to assume that this is
tangent here here and here if you want
to try it on your own pause it right now
cuz I'm going to solve it in 3 2 1 so
let's copy this down here and I'm going
to leave the circle yellow here because
I'm going to be writing in here these
two circles are tangent right here so
let's construct the tangent line between
the two circles and then I'm also
assuming this is tangent right here so
let's draw this tangent line there's a
special property if you have two
tangents to a circle if the tangents
intersect these two distances are the
same so if we go up here let's shorten
this tangent line and shorten this
tangent line and then since these are
both tangent lines to the same Circle
there the same length and then if we
take this line and make it all red we
now have a nice looking red triangle and
it's an isoceles triangle since these
two sides are congruent that means these
two base angles are congruent let's call
them both a degrees let's clean this up
and let's give ourselves some room
because we're going to look at this
other tangent line and we're going to
extend it all the way up here this red
distance and this red distance will also
be equal to each other and if we
complete this right here we have another
cool looking red triangle that's also is
oses since these two sides are congruent
the base angles are congruent let's give
them both a measure of B de and now
let's clean this up and then this angle
right here is made up of b and a we can
make it a single angle of B+ a de and
this B+ a degrees that is our question
mark so we can say question mark is
equal to B+ a de this looks important
let's put a box around it and let's move
it down here next let's focus on this
quadrilateral right here this angle will
be a right angle because of the
rectangle and let's focus on our new
quadrilateral the sum of the interior
angles of any quadrilateral is
360° so we can say 90 + a plus a plus b
plus b equal 360 then let's subtract 90
from both sides on the left hand side
these are gone a plus a is 2 a B plus b
is 2b and then on the right hand side
360 - 90 is 270 then we can divide both
sides by 2 on the left hand side this is
A + B and on the right hand side 270 / 2
is 135 so now we know a + b is equal to
135 and our question mark was B plus a
we can switch these and now in the place
of B plus a we can plug in 135 so this
is the answer to her question this angle
is going to be
135° let's put a box around it how
exciting this is the answer to day 11
this is the puzzle for day 12 it says
what's the area of the semi semicircle
inside this equilateral triangle so
we're given that this circle six we're
given that's an equilateral triangle
that's super helpful and then we're
given this semicircle this will be a fun
one how exciting